Now, if President Obama
الآن، لو أن الرئيس أوباما
invited me to be the next Czar of Mathematics,
دعاني لأكون القيصر القادم للرياضيات
then I would have a suggestion for him
حينها سيكون لدي إقتراح
that I think would vastly improve
أعتقد أنه سيحسن كثيرا
the mathematics education in this country.
تعليم الرياضيات في هذه الدولة
And it would be easy to implement
وسيكون تطبيق ذلك سهلا
and inexpensive.
وغير مكلف
The mathematics curriculum that we have
إن منهج الرياضيات لدينا
is based on a foundation of arithmetic and algebra.
مبني على أسس الحساب والجبر
And everything we learn after that
وكل ما نتعلمه بعد ذلك
is building up towards one subject.
يبني بغية الوصول لموضوع واحد
And at top of that pyramid, it's calculus.
وفي أعلى ذلك الهرم حساب التفاضل والتكامل
And I'm here to say
وأنا هنا لأقول
that I think that that is the wrong summit of the pyramid ...
أن هذه قمة خاطئة للهرم
that the correct summit -- that all of our students,
وأن القمة الصحيحة -- التي على كل طلابنا
every high school graduate should know --
كل خريجي الثانوية يجب أن يعرفوها -ـ
should be statistics:
يجب أن تكون الإحصاء
probability and statistics.
الإحتمالات والإحصاء
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I mean, don't get me wrong. Calculus is an important subject.
أعني، لا تفهموني خطأ. فالتفاضل والتكامل موضوع مهم
It's one of the great products of the human mind.
إنها أحد النتائج العظيمة للعقل البشري
The laws of nature are written in the language of calculus.
قوانين الطبيعة مكتوبة بلغة التفاضل والتكامل
And every student who studies math, science, engineering, economics,
وكل طالب يدرس الرياضيات، العلوم، الهندسة والإقتصاد
they should definitely learn calculus
عليهم بكل تأكيد تعلم التفاضل والتكامل
by the end of their freshman year of college.
بنهاية سنتهم الأولى في الكلية
But I'm here to say, as a professor of mathematics,
ولكنني هنا لأقول، كبروفيسور رياضيات
that very few people actually use calculus
أن عدد محدود جدا من الناس يستخدمون التفاضل والتكامل
in a conscious, meaningful way, in their day-to-day lives.
بطريقة واعية و مفيدة في حياتهم اليومية
On the other hand,
في المقابل
statistics -- that's a subject that you could,
الإحصاء -- هذا موضوع يمكنك
and should, use on daily basis. Right?
بل عليك أن تستخدمه يوميا. صحيح؟
It's risk. It's reward. It's randomness.
إنها المخاطر. إنها العائد . إنها العشوائية
It's understanding data.
إنها فهم البيانات
I think if our students, if our high school students --
أعتقد لو أن طلبتنا، لو أن طلبة الثانوية
if all of the American citizens --
لو أن جميع المواطنين الأمريكان
knew about probability and statistics,
علموا عن الإحتمالات والإحصاء
we wouldn't be in the economic mess that we're in today. (Laughter) (Applause)
لما كنا في الفوضى الإقتصادية التي وصلنا إليها اليوم
Not only -- thank you -- not only that ...
ليس فقط -- شكرا -- ليس ذلك فقط
but if it's taught properly, it can be a lot of fun.
ولكن لو أنها درست بشكل صحيح، يمكن أن تكون ممتعة جدا
I mean, probability and statistics,
أعني، الإحتمالات والإحصاء
it's the mathematics of games and gambling.
إنها رياضيات الألعاب والمقامرة
It's analyzing trends. It's predicting the future.
إنها تحليل التيارات. إنها التنبؤ بالمستقبل
Look, the world has changed
تأملوا، العالم قد تغير
from analog to digital.
من التناظرية إلى الرقمية
And it's time for our mathematics curriculum to change
وقد آن الأوان لمناهج الرياضيات أن تتغير
from the more classical, continuous mathematics,
من الرياضيات الكلاسيكية المستمرة
to the more modern, discrete mathematics --
للأكثر حداثة، الرياضيات المتقطعة
the mathematics of uncertainty,
رياضيات المجهول
of randomness, of data --
عشوائية البيانات
that being probability and statistics.
وتلك هي الإحتمالات والإحصاء
In summary, instead of our students
باختصار ، بدلا من أن يدرس
learning about the techniques of calculus,
طلابنا تقنيات التفاضل والتكامل
I think it would be far more significant
أعتقد أن وقعها سيكون أكبر بكثير
if all of them knew what two standard deviations
لو أنهم جميعا علموا ما يعنيه
from the mean means. And I mean it.
إنحرافين معياريين من المتوسط. وأنا أعني ذلك
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)